谁拥有香料
谁就拥有世界
帝国日记 10191年 评论三
Imperial diary, year 10191, third comment.
厄拉科斯之战举世震惊
The battle for Arrakis took everyone by surprise.
没有目击者
There were no witnesses.
哈克南人的行动是在
The Harkonnen operation was perpetrated
未经警告或宣战的情况下 趁夜间进行的
overnight without warning or declaration of war.
到了早上 厄崔迪家族被消灭殆尽
By morning, the Atreides were no more.
悉数殒命长夜
All died in the dark.
而皇帝……
And the Emperor said...
沉默无语
Nothing.
从那天晚上起 我父亲就变了
Since that night my father has not been the same.
我也是
Nor have I.
他的哀伤憔悴让我心如刀割
His inaction is difficult for me to accept.
因为我知道他像爱儿子一样爱着雷托·厄崔迪公爵
For I know he loved Duke Leto Atreides, like a son
但我父亲总是为权力所困
But my father has always been guided by the calculus of power.
这已经不是第一次
This would not be the first time the
哈克南家族为他做的肮脏勾当
Harkonnens have done his dirty work.
在厄拉科斯星球的阴影下埋藏着许多秘密
In the shadows of Arrakis lie many secrets.
但其中最黑暗的可能就是……
But the darkest of them all may remain...
厄崔迪家族的末日
The end of House Atreides.
【 沙 丘 第 二 部 】
妹妹
Sister.
父亲死了
Father is dead.
你不是应该回到星际去吗？
Shouldn't you go back to the stars?
和他在一起
Be with him.
恐怕我没有足够的时间
I'm afraid I won't have enough time to
在你降生之前处理好事情
fix things before you're coming.
这个世界无比残酷
This world is beyond cruelty.
敌人
待在这儿
Stay here.
右下方
他们就在附近
听到了吗？
老鼠在召唤沙虫
沙虫！
全体 爬上去 快！
注意沙虫迹象
安全
打开屏蔽场！
没有屏蔽场！
哪里跑 老鼠
永远不要背对敌人站着
Never stand with your back towards the opponent.
我跟你说过多少回了？
How many times do I have to tell you that?
你没事吧？
You okay?
没
No.
她怎样？
How about her?
她很好
She's fine.
他们通常不这么深入
They do not usually venture this deep.
他们想把厄崔迪家族斩草除根 赶尽杀绝
They want to make sure no Atreides escaped.
你太自以为是了
You think too much of yourself.
不 不 我们在沙漠深处
No, no, we are in the deep desert.
只有弗雷曼人才能在这里生存
Only Fremen can survive here.
他们是来找我们的 不是来找你们的
They were here for us, not for you.
别担心
Don't worry.
我带你们去一个他们永远找不到的地方
I'm taking you somewhere they will never find us.
脏水
Filthy water.
里面全是化学物质 不过
It's full of chemicals, but
用于冷却系统还可以
good enough for cooling system.
别吐出来
Don't let it out.
你没事吧？
You okay?
别吐出来
Don't let it out.
差一点
I can't.
我没事
I'm okay.
你确定？
Are you sure?
你打得很好
You fought well.
一旦你醒来
Once you woke up.
我没睡着
I wasn't sleeping.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
我来吧
I'll do it.
阿拉肯 北厄拉科斯星球首府
拉 拉班大人
Lord Raban.
现在香料田已经安全了
Now that the spice field are secured,
我强烈建议将所有军队
I strongly recommend bringing all troops
撤出弗雷曼人的区域
out of Fremen territories.
我们在沙漠里损失了太多人
We're losing too many men to the desert
老鼠
Rats.
你说什么？
I beg your pardon?
我们损失的人……
We're losing them...
给了老鼠
To rats.
弗雷曼人
Fremen.
我无法确认 大人
I can't confirm, my Lord.
在开阔的沙地上通讯很混乱
Communications are hectic in the open sands.
你的任务
Your orders,
是控制整个星球
were too control the whole the planet.
我们有……
We have–
这只是一半
That's only half of it.
你可能还记得 南方不适合居住 大人
As you may recall, the south is uninhabtable, my Lord
我建议你休息一下 好吗？
May I suggest you get some rest?
老鼠！
Rats!
杀光他们！
Kill them all!
老鼠！
Rats!
他问我们为什么迟到了
He's asking why we're so late.
他认为你们是间谍
He thinks you're spies.
这里不欢迎你们
他说……
He said...
我听懂了
I got that.
谢谢
Thanks.
跟紧我
Stay close to me.
塔布尔穴地
Sietch Tabr
詹米! 詹米！
你杀了詹米！
间谍！
女巫！
住手! 住手！
他们不知道自己在说什么
李桑·阿尔-盖布! 李桑·阿尔-盖布！
救世主！
我需要你指引我们怎么处理那两个外国人
把他们交给沙漠
我看到了征兆
又来了
斯第尔格 你的信仰蒙蔽了你的双眼
李桑·阿尔-盖布还没出世呢！
他在一场公平的决斗中战胜了詹米
他会说我们的语言
他很快就会学会我们的生存之道
我愿意为他献出生命
沙漠将决定他的命运
那个女人呢？
看来贝尼·杰瑟里特的宣传已经深入人心
Looks like the Bene Gesserit's ' propaganda has taken root
有些人已经认为我是他们的救世主了
Some of them already think I'm their messiah.
其他人 则认为我是假先知
Others, false prophet.
我必须说服那些不信的人
I must sway the non-believers.
如果他们跟着我 我们就可以
If they follow me, we can
破坏香料生产
disrupt spice production.
只有这条路我才能接近皇帝
That's the only way I can get to the emperor.
你父亲不相信复仇
Your father didn't believe in revenge.
我相信
Hell, I do.
怎么了？
What is happening?
外国人吃不了辣？
怎么回事？
What is it?
食物里有香料
There's spice in the food.
他蓝眼睛一定很好看
别嘲笑他
他值得我们尊重 他是个好战士
女人 跟我来
Woman, come with me.
放回井里 我们的水回来了
我们祝福我们的兄弟 詹米
三千八百万公升
38 million decaliters.
我们即使渴死
None of us, even dying of thirst
也不会喝这的水
would ever drink this water.
这是神圣的
This is sacred.
创世纪之水
Genesis water.
我们有几千个这样的地方
We have thousands of places.
我们有足够的水源
where we have enough water.
李桑·阿尔-盖布将会
The Lisan al-Gaib will
改变厄拉科斯星球的面貌
Change the face of Arrakis
它将使树木重生 它将使……
It will bring back trees, it will bring back...
绿色天堂重现
a green paradise.
这么多灵魂
So many souls
永远不要把你的水给别人
Never give your water away,
即使死人也不行
not even for the dead.
你为什么带我看这些？
Why are you showing me this?
因为你是贝尼·杰瑟里特
Because you are Bene Gesserit
因为你了解预言
Because you understand the prophecies.
李桑·阿尔-盖布的母亲
The mother of the Lisan al-Gaib
会成为圣母
will be a Reverend mother.
我们的圣母快死了
Our Reverend Mother is dying.
你想让我代替她？
You want me to take her place?
是的
Yes,
我想
I do.
你相信保罗吗？
Do you believe in Paul?
有征兆
There are signs.
是的
Yes.
如果我拒绝呢？
What if I would refuse?
那他就不是李桑·阿尔-盖布
Then he is not Lisan al-Gaib,
你就没有任何意义了
And you have no purpose to serve.
那你还能做什么？
What else is left to do then?
把你的水放回井里？
But return your water to the well?
这是种荣誉 不是吗？
It's an honor, isn't it?
我觉得你应该感到荣幸
I think you should feel honored.
这是生死决择
It was a choice between this or death,
所以请原谅我的不敬
so forgive me if I'm not flattered.
一个人怎样才能当上圣母？
How does one become a Reverend Mother?
不同的文化是不同的
It's different from one culture to another.
在厄拉科斯星球 我不知道
Here on Arrakis, I have no idea.
你害怕了
You're afraid.
圣母肩负着
A Reverend Mother has the task
保存他们以前历代圣母的
of holding the memories
全部记忆的使命
of all the Reverend Mothers that came before them,
所以我会被赐予几个世纪的痛苦与悲伤
so I'll be given centuries of pain and sorrow.
危险吗？
Is it dangerous?
对男人来说是致命的
It's lethal for men.
绝对是
That's for sure.
你们在笑什么？
What are you guys laughing about?
别管了
Don't bother.
你不相信这一切？
You don't believe in all this?
不 我们不信
No, we don't.
这些都是南方的信仰
These are all Southern beliefs.
南方的信仰？
Southern beliefs?
南方部落相信弥赛亚
Southern tribes believe that a Messiah
会来拯救我们脱离邪恶
will come to deliver us from evil.
你不相信李桑·阿尔-盖布？
You don't believe in the Lisan al-Gaib?
我们相信弗雷曼人
We believe in Fremen
阿门
你想控制别人？
You want to control people?
你告诉他们救世主会来
You tell them a Messiah will come.
然后他们会等上几个世纪
Then they'll wait, for centuries.
现在 我们必须祈祷
Now, we must pray.
他怎么了？
What about him?
斯第尔格？
Stilgar?
他是南方人
He's from the South.
你没注意到他的口音
You didn't notice his accent.
我妈妈会怎么样？
What'll happen to my mother?
她会喝沙虫的尿
一点都不好笑
他就要失去她了
如果她蠢到喝毒药的话
住口！住口！
我们在祈祷
这是生命之水
它能解放心灵
如果你喝的话
你就会死去
你可以看见
喝！
这是什么？
我们做了什么？
她怀孕了
那不是奇迹！
你亲眼看到的！
李桑·阿尔-盖布的母亲
将在神圣的毒药试炼中幸存
她做到了
像书上写的那样！
那是她的族人写的！
亵渎神明
预言已经实现了
救世主必须是弗雷曼人！
厄拉科斯必须由自己的人民来解放！
她说得对 她说得对
She's right.
这不是奇迹
It's no miracle.
我妈妈受过这方面的训练
My mother was trained to do that.
把毒素转化成别的东西
Poison transmutation is something
高级贝尼·杰瑟里特可以做到
advanced Bene Gesserit can do.
我不是救世主
I'm not the Mahdi.
我不是来领导的
I'm not here to lead.
我是来学习你们的生存之道的
我在这里与你们并肩作战
I'm here to fight beside you.
这是我唯一的要求
That's all I'm asking.
我很谦虚地说他是救世主
更有理由相信他是！
像书上写的那样！
她怎么样？
How is she?
她很害怕 但她没事
She was frightened but she's okay.
她跟我说话
She talks to me.
她相信你
She believes in you.
她说
She says
魁萨茨·哈德拉克给我们指明道路
你就快成功了
You're so close now.
只有一步之遥
Only one step remains.
你会成为魁萨茨·哈德拉克
you will become the Kwisatz Haderach.
只有一步之遥
Only one step remains.
你必须像我一样
You must do what I did.
你必须喝下生命之水
You must drink the water of life.
你会解放心灵 你将看见
Your mind is gonna open and you will see.
你将看见！
美丽与恐怖！
如果你想和我们并肩战斗
If you want to fight with us,
首先你必须学会
first thing you must learn
与沙漠融为一体
to be one with the desert.
这里有帐篷和足够的食物
So here is a tent and enough food.
我要你走到那个小沙丘 然后返回
I want you to cross that small erg and come back.
晚上回来
Come by night.
你知道怎么用指南针
You know how to use a paracompass.
会的
Yes.
还有什么我需要知道的吗？
Anything else I should know?
除了沙虫和哈克南人
Beside the worms and the Harkonnens,
小心土蜘蛛
beware of the trap door spiders.
蜈蚣也很讨厌
Centipedes are very nasty.
不是那些大的
Not the big ones.
大的无害
They are harmless.
但小的你就要注意了
But the little ones you have to worry about.
千万 千万别听巨灵的话
Don't ever, ever listen to the Djinn.
巨灵
The Djinn.
巨灵 沙漠之魂
Djinn, desert spirits.
他们在夜晚轻言细语
They whisper at night.
他们会魅惑你
They can possess you.
真的 小心点
Really, be careful.
他们是恶魔
They are demons.
但这是真的
But it's true.
别听他们的
Don't listen to them.
他不知道如何穿越沙地
斯第尔格会害死他的
他想证明什么？
你觉得呢？
“先知必知道沙漠的道路”
我觉得这样最好
是不是这样？
你现在关心他了？
他和其他陌生人不一样
他很真诚
詹米
Jamis
你走起路来像只喝醉的蜥蜴
You sand walk like a drunk lizard.
是么 目前为止我做得还不赖
Yeah, I'm doing pretty good so far.
我们还没进入沙虫的地盘呢
We're not even in worm territory yet.
你得打破你的节奏
You have to break up your rhythm.
像这样
Like this.
这很有趣 因为在胶片书里
Now that's interesting because in the film books
我研究过 人类学家说
I've studied, the anthropologists say in order
你必须按照一定的规律，才能在沙地上行走
to properly sand walk, you actually have to.
算了
Nevermind.
请继续
Please keep going.
你知道 我是唯一一个相信
You know, I'm the only one who believes
你会撑到夏天的人
you're gonna make it until summer.
如果你想在沙漠里跟上我们
If you wanna follow us in the desert,
你就得知道捕风器的原理
you need to know how wind traps work.
所以听我说
So listen to me.
我总是觉得很简单
It's always neat to me.
它们很简单 但需要时刻留意
They're simple, but they require constant attention.
啥？
What?
别这样看着我
Stop looking at me like that.
你说得对
You're right.
如果我们想保护你的哥哥
If we want to protect your brother,
我们需要所有弗雷曼人都相信预言
we need all the Fremen to believe in the prophecy.
我们必须一个接一个地改变不信者的信仰
We must convert the non-believers one by one.
我们得从弱者开始
We need to start with the weaker ones.
意志簿弱的人
the vulnerable ones.
那些害怕我们的人
The ones that fear us.
契妮！
Chani!
装弹
Reload.
屏蔽场 只有直升机开火时才会关闭
The shield. They only open when they're firing.
我知道
I know that.
你以为我在做什么？
What do you think I'm trying to do?
我做引子
I'm triggering.
等我信号
On my signal.
准备
Be ready.
哦 该死
Oh shit.
你看到他做了什么
他早就料到了
他救了她的命
他看到了
他能预见
穆阿迪布喜欢他的味道
谁教你这样战斗的？
Who taught you to fight like that?
我以前的师傅
My old masters.
他们是很要好的朋友
And they were close friends.
他们被屠杀了 和我父亲一起
They were a massacred. Alongside my father.
你们与哈克南人作战几十年
You've been fighting The Harkonnens for decades.
我的家族已经与他们争斗了几个世纪
My family has been fighting them for centuries.
他们的习惯 他们的思维方式 我了如指掌
Their habits, their ways of thinking. I know everything about them,
你们对沙漠了如指掌
You know everything about the desert.
你们驾驭沙漠的力量
You harness the very power of it.
我们可以一起阻止他们
We can stop them together.
让他们死无丧身之沙
Bury them in the sand where they belong.
让这个星球再次属于你们
So that this planet can be yours once more.
你要我们做什么？
What will you have us do?
你会怎么做 斯第尔格？
What would you do, Stilgar?
我会挥戈北上
I would strike even further north.
那我挥戈北上
Then I will go further north.
你越往北走
The further north you go,
你越可能死
the more likely it is you die.
我会死
也许你也会死
但其他人会继续前进
直到弗雷曼人获得自由为止 否则他们是不会罢休的
他应该加入弗雷曼敢死队
他需要个名字 斯第尔格
好样的！好样的！
我在你身上看到了力量
I see strength in you.
像友索一样
意思是“梁柱的底座”
过来 过来
Come, come.
在我们中间 你应该被称为友索
You shall be known among us as Usul.
友索
Usul.
现在 你加入了弗雷曼敢死队 成为一名战士
And now a Fedaykin is a fighter.
你还必须选一个
and needs a war name.
战斗用的名字
You must choose.
你们怎么称呼这只沙漠小老鼠来着？
How do you call the small desert mouse again?
穆阿迪布 穆阿迪布
Muad'Dib.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
哦 不 穆阿迪布是很聪明的
Oh no, Muad'Dib is wise.
穆阿迪布深知沙漠的生存之道
Muad'dib is wise in the ways of the desert.
穆阿迪布 能自己制造水
Muad'Dib creates his own water.
能辩别指向北方的星座
The constellation that points to the North
所以我们叫它穆阿迪布
we call Muad'Dib.
指引方向的人
The one who points the way.
这名字很有力量
That is powerful name.
现在你是我们的兄弟了
Now you are our brother.
保罗·穆阿迪布·友索
Paul Muad'Dib Usul.
嘿! 斯第尔格！
Hey! Stilgar!
父亲 我找到了自己的路
Father, I found my way.
真美啊
It's breathtaking.
看 这就是香料
Look, right there's spice
每当夕阳落暮的时候 厄拉科斯星球格外动人
Arrakis is so beautiful when the sun is low.
在你的家乡
Where you're from...
水真的是从天而降的吗？
Does water really fall from the sky?
哦 是的
Oh, yes.
卡拉丹有时会下一个星期的雨
Sometimes it rains for a weeks, in Caladan
你看这儿的沙子 想象全是水
Where you see sand here, imagine water.
我们的城堡就矗立在海边的悬崖上
Our castle stands on cliffs, over the sea.
就算你一头扎进去 也够不到底
If you dive in, you can't reach the bottom.
你跳进去了？
You dive in?
是的
Yes.
这叫游泳
It's called swimming.
我可不相信 友索
I don't believe you, Usul.